Hello, my friends, and welcome to exercise number 93.
And this exercise, we are asked to optimize the complexity of bubbles saw in the previous video.
We have created the bubble sort algorithm in a function called bubble sorting and took into the parameters
that array that we are going to serve.
And we have said that our complexity of this algorithm would be awe and squish always.
So.
I need to think about this.
What we need, what we need to optimize in order to make and reduce this complex.
This is in the best case and the worst case scenario is or in the square.
OK.
Because every time we are going to loop through that elements in a nested loop.
OK, so.
Where is the trick in order to save the time and order to save that complexity and searching algorithms
and searching for that and sorting out these where?
The answer is if I passed a.
Sorted.
Let me show you one two one two four five six eight.
If I run the program.
It would be sort because it didn't do anything, but it loops through this in a time complexity and
square.
So even if the array is not sorted is given sorted.
We have a complexity on the square and this is not acceptable as a professional coder and a professional
broker.
So what we need to do?
We need to make here.
Anne Boleyn.
Swabs called swab and inside the outer loop, we start by initializing swab equal to false because this
will indicate if we have done is swapping or not.
OK, no.
If.
We do a swab then inside the if here, if condition, we need to change the strap to do OK.
This is their algorithm, this is the usage of usage of Boolean, which lies at the falls.
And even if we have swiped anything, we put it it's value to swap.
So where is where the usage of this?
Why we have done a Boolean, why we are increasing that is variables because I need to use it here.
So after the loop, we check.
If after the first two.
The inner loop, if it is, go through all the elements and then to swept anything before continuing
the outer alliteration and make that complexity and the square, we need to make that condition here.
If no, if no swapping of two elements
like happens happened,
then.
Break.
Break the loop.
If swept equal equal to falls, then break.
This is the condition that that if if I run here, let me show you if I have a sort that added a one
two, three, four, five, six and eight.
After sorting, it is the same.
If I print the value of swapped system to print the value of swab, let me show you and then I will
lecture for you what we have done.
Bubbles or the sweat.
Let me make as.
OK, probably.
Static.
Here.
I will make it as a class member.
I was sort of swept through Nancy.
And here, after sorting swept is false because we didn't made any sweeping.
So this is why we didn't make any sweeping and that air raid that we have passed is already scrapped
already is already sorted.
So it reduces our complexity from the grill going through all the elements from the outer loop and the
inner loop and maybe that complexity or and the square.
If we pass now as sorted, every then it will reduce our complexity.
Time, complexity front and square to all of this is now in the worst case, worst case scenario.
And this is the best case.
OK.
Best case.
We have same sorting thing sorted out.
OK.
You see, guys, how we have optimized our algorithm, how we have worked.
And then.
Checking if there is a sorting error, I have reduced the complexity from all around the square.
We don't we don't go every time to iterate through all the elements and then we move the iterator eye
and then go through all the elements and we have made a wasted work.
So we are not wasting time.
We are here to make algorithms and algorithm works perfect and reducing its complexity from any square
to end or end Logan or analog.
So this is our mission.
This is why we need to understand that we need to make a perfect, a scalable, efficient.